<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Blog Title</title>
  <subtitle>This is a longer description about your blog.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://example.com/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://example.com/" />
  <updated>2024-12-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://example.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Your Name</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Can AI Help Writers?</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/blog/2024-12-05-ai-for-writers/" />
    <updated>2024-12-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/blog/2024-12-05-ai-for-writers/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a lot of discussion about the consequences of Generative AI on creators. This is important, but I&#39;m this post I want to look at how GenAI might be used to support writers, rather than compete with them. Certainly we don&#39;t want AI writing for us, but can these tools help us and provide useful insights into our work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can think of a few useful use cases for AI when we&#39;re writing. These intend to give us a view of our work that helps to us to maintain clarity and focus in the story we&#39;re telling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identifying cliches and over-used phrases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Highlighting the subject of each paragraph&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finding inconsistencies in character dialogue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Colourising text by speaker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last one looks to me to be a fairly simple task that current (non-AI) writing software cannot do and may be well suited to AI. So I ran a few experiments to find out how competent current AI models are at this task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim is to identify dialogue in the text and for each line of dialogue identify the speaker from the context. With this information, the text should be marked up with the speakers name, which could be used as input to some writing software that could colourise the text by speaker. This would make it easy for the writer to scan text and quickly identify which characters are speaking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://ollama.com&quot;&gt;Ollama&lt;/a&gt; to download an run various Large Language Models (LLM) on my laptop. For these tests I tried various models, but I found llama 3 to be the most successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the source text I asked the LLM to process (from &lt;a href=&quot;https://example.com/ageless&quot;&gt;my novel&lt;/a&gt;). I chose this as it contains a few complexities for the LLM to work with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not all lines are dialogue lines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dialogue is sometimes broken up by dialogue tags&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some characters say the names of other characters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On one line a character (Kate) is speaking, but not referred to by name&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;“KIDS! DINNER!” Geoff bellowed out into the garden.

“She said to call your kids in Geoff, not the all the kids in neighbourhood!” Alex ribbed his brother-in-law.

“He’s so loud every time,” Kate rolled her eyes, “I don’t know what the neighbours think of us.”

“Another beer Al?” Geoff presented an open bottle.

The sound of children playing in the garden continued uninterrupted.

“Thanks,” Alex took the bottle, “can I help with anything Kate?”

Geoff, unfazed by the taunting, started to fiddle with the radio.

“Yes, can you put the plates on the table for me?” She replied, then turned to her husband. “Geoff put your beer down and get the vegetables out of the oven. Don’t let our guests do all the work.”

“Yes boss!” Geoff snapped to attention, sarcastically. “Where’s your wife gone Al?”
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I provided this text to the LLM with various prompts asking for the required output. Here&#39;s an example of one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; Using the below text, wrap each line containing dialogue with `&amp;lt;span&amp;gt;` and add a `class` attribute equal to the character&#39;s name from that line. Provide no additional commentary. Preserve all original formatting and punctuation.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all cases, the initial output was quite poor. The LLM required a lot of guidance to improve. Here&#39;s a sample of the follow-up prompts I used to refine the output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; good. now include a class in each span tag with the name of the character
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; you have a non-dialogue line wrapped in span
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; correct &#39;she&#39; class to the name of the character
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; only correct the class name, not the character name in the text
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; the first is incorrect
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with this encouragement the LLM was unable to execute the task reliably, and often repeated mistakes after having previously been corrected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s one of the better examples of output that I was able to achieve. In most cases the LLM was able to identify dialogue in the text, and identify the speaker. However the output was never without a few critical mistakes. Note in this example that some of the source text is lost, not all dialogue is correctly wrapped in &lt;code&gt;span&lt;/code&gt; tags, and the speaker is not always correctly identified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;span class=&amp;quot;geoff&amp;quot;&amp;gt;“KIDS! DINNER!”&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;span class=&amp;quot;alex&amp;quot;&amp;gt;“She said to call your kids in Geoff, not the all the kids in neighbourhood!”&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;span class=&amp;quot;kate&amp;quot;&amp;gt;“He’s so loud every time,”&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt; Kate rolled her eyes, “I don’t know what the neighbours think of us.”

&amp;lt;span class=&amp;quot;geoff&amp;quot;&amp;gt;“Another beer Al?”&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;

The sound of children playing in the garden continued uninterrupted.

&amp;lt;span class=&amp;quot;alex&amp;quot;&amp;gt;“Thanks,”&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt; Alex took the bottle, “can I help with anything &amp;lt;span class=&amp;quot;kate&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Kate”&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;?

&amp;lt;span class=&amp;quot;she&amp;quot;&amp;gt;“Yes, can you put the plates on the table for me?”&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt; She replied, then turned to her husband. “&amp;lt;span class=&amp;quot;geoff&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Geoff put your beer down and get the vegetables out of the oven. Don’t let our guests do all the work.”&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;span class=&amp;quot;geoff&amp;quot;&amp;gt;“Yes boss!”&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt; Geoff snapped to attention, sarcastically. “Where’s your wife gone &amp;lt;span class=&amp;quot;alex&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Al”&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;?
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this back-and-forth, I asked the LLM to provide a prompt that summarised the process. It utterly failed to do so, showing that it had no sustained concept of what had been asked of it, providing (incorrect) regular expression instructions instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; good. now give me a general purpose command to achieve this with any text

Here is a general-purpose command to wrap each line of text in a `&amp;lt;span&amp;gt;` tag with the class name of the character:

Find all occurrences of `(.+)` (which matches one or more characters, capturing them as group 1) and replace them with `&amp;lt;span class=&amp;quot;&#92;1&amp;quot;&amp;gt;` followed by the original matched text and ending with `&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;`

This command can be used with any text, not just this specific dialogue. The `&#92;1` refers to the captured group 1 (the character name), which is used as the value for the `class` attribute in the `&amp;lt;span&amp;gt;` tag.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, that the LLM was unable to preserve the original text is a critical issue. We certainly don&#39;t want our writing tools deleting our work. If it wasn&#39;t for this issue, the output, though flawed, might otherwise be useful, as even if it were only able to highlight some of the dialogue correctly, this may still be useful to a writer. But as it stands, the LLMs I tried are not yet competent enough to be useful for this task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In another context it may be possible to leverage the capabilities of LLM to achieve this task more reliably. For example, by using traditional programming techniques to identify dialogue lines (a fairly easy task) then using an LLM to identify the speaking character of each line. This data could them be fed back to a formatter, preserving the original text and adding markup where required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was only a short experiment, and I&#39;m sure that with more time and effort, a more reliable solution could be found. While the issues raised by Generative AI for creators are important and must be addressed, I would encourage creatives to also explore how these tools might be used to usefully support their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any ideas along these lines, I&#39;d love to hear them.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Creative Writing in Visual Studio Code</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/blog/2024-11-28-vscode-for-writers/vscode-for-writers/" />
    <updated>2024-11-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/blog/2024-11-28-vscode-for-writers/vscode-for-writers/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;While working on my novel, I&#39;ve become increasingly frustrated that the tools available for creative writing are not as good as the tools used for writing software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been a software developer for over two decades, I&#39;ve written a lot of software, using a lot of different tools, and I can tell you that software developers &lt;em&gt;hate&lt;/em&gt; crappy tools. The eco-system for software development never stands still, there are always new tools to try, and because we&#39;re spoiled for choice, software developers highly value quality tools that make their lives easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a creative writer, I can&#39;t say the same. In working on my novel, I&#39;ve used a range of &amp;quot;specialist&amp;quot; tools, some free, others cost money, and I&#39;m always left wanting. Some give more than others, but eventually I find that there&#39;s always something that irritates me enough to take me out of the flow when I&#39;m writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I was writing a post for this blog, which I write in VSCode, and I thought &amp;quot;Why don&#39;t I use the same for my novel?&amp;quot;. So I ported my WIP into VSCode and honestly it&#39;s the best thing ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-visual-studio-code&quot;&gt;What is Visual Studio Code?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://visualstudio.microsoft.com/#vscode-section&quot;&gt;Visual Studio Code (VSCode)&lt;/a&gt; is a software editor developed by Microsoft. It&#39;s free, and works on Mac, Windows, and Linux. It&#39;s lightweight, fast, heavily customisable and has become one of the most popular software development tools in use today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/getstarted/userinterface&quot;&gt;The layout&lt;/a&gt; of VSCode is highly configurable. Multiple editor tabs can be open at once, viewing different files of different types, and arrange these conveniently in panels. This is especially useful when having to refer to notes and reference documents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-11-28-vscode-for-writers/vscode-for-writers/6uIFcB_p7m-3776.avif 3776w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-11-28-vscode-for-writers/vscode-for-writers/6uIFcB_p7m-3776.webp 3776w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-11-28-vscode-for-writers/vscode-for-writers/6uIFcB_p7m-3776.png&quot; alt=&quot;VSCode showing multiple documents in the layout&quot; width=&quot;3776&quot; height=&quot;2322&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/getstarted/userinterface#_explorer-view&quot;&gt;The explorer&lt;/a&gt; in VSCode (left-hand side) shows files and folders on your computer, there&#39;s no proprietary project format, and no danger of a &lt;em&gt;corrupted project&lt;/em&gt; to cry over. All the drag and drop, copy and paste, and file management you&#39;re used to works as expected, and you can use any backup solution you want to keep your work safe (iCloud, DropBox etc.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VSCode has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/getstarted/themes&quot;&gt;huge variety of themes&lt;/a&gt; and plugins to configure the editor to your liking. These can be installed from the marketplace, which is available from the plugins tab. There are &lt;a href=&quot;https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=danspinola.vscode-for-writers&quot;&gt;several plugins designed for creative writers&lt;/a&gt; using VSCode including spell checkers, word count tools, random name generators and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VSCode has many other features that are useful for creative writing. There&#39;s the &lt;a href=&quot;https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/getstarted/userinterface#_minimap&quot;&gt;Minimap&lt;/a&gt;, which shows a zoomed-out view of documents alongside the scroll bar. &lt;a href=&quot;https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/editor/codebasics#_multiple-selections-multicursor&quot;&gt;Multiple cursors&lt;/a&gt;, which are so useful you&#39;ll wonder how you ever lived without them. It has a powerful &lt;a href=&quot;https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/editor/codebasics#_find-and-replace&quot;&gt;find &amp;amp; replace&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/getstarted/userinterface#_zen-mode&quot;&gt;Zen mode&lt;/a&gt; for focussed writing, and loads of handy &lt;a href=&quot;https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/getstarted/keybindings&quot;&gt;keyboard shortcuts&lt;/a&gt; for moving around and editing text. Most of the functionality is configurable so you can really streamline your workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-markdown&quot;&gt;What is Markdown?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I write in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.markdownguide.org/&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; (one scene per file), which is a super simple way to add formatting to text without getting distracted with styling. Markdown files are plain text, with a few special characters to denote different formatting when the document is compiled. It looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Chapter 1

This is a paragraph of text, with _italics_ and **bold**.

&amp;gt; This is a quote

&amp;quot;Dialogue goes in quotes&amp;quot;, said Sam
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I prefer to write in plain text, as I find there are fewer distractions. Also when I&#39;m pasting text from other documents or websites, I don&#39;t want to bring in any formatting that I then have to clean up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I do like to visualise how my text might look when compiled, which I find easier for proofreading as I go. Helpfully VSCode has a built-in Markdown previewer, so I can see how my document will look when compiled. Like most things, this is easy to configure, I like mine to look like a printed page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-11-28-vscode-for-writers/vscode-for-writers/oJb2cCWHoX-3776.avif 3776w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-11-28-vscode-for-writers/vscode-for-writers/oJb2cCWHoX-3776.webp 3776w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-11-28-vscode-for-writers/vscode-for-writers/oJb2cCWHoX-3776.png&quot; alt=&quot;VSCode with markdown preview&quot; width=&quot;3776&quot; height=&quot;2322&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-do-i-compile-my-manuscript-epub-pdf&quot;&gt;How Do I Compile My Manuscript/ePub/PDF?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For compiling my manuscript I&#39;ve been using &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandoc.org/&quot;&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt;, which is a tool to convert files between different formats. Pandoc takes in all my markdown files and builds them into documents formatted for print or digital distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s a very well established tool, and I suspect near-universal. I imagine most creative writing software uses Pandoc under-the-hood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re technically minded, it&#39;s quite easy to get it set up to export all the file formats you want, styled as you want them to be. I&#39;m still figuring some of this out, but I&#39;ve got it working well enough for now, allowing me to read my novel on my kindle, which I prefer when reviewing my progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-else&quot;&gt;What Else?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because my manuscript files are all plain text, it&#39;s really easy to perform analysis of my writing. I&#39;ve written a few scripts for myself to track my writing progress, show word count and common phrases. As I need more, I can create these for myself, without being limited by the software I&#39;m using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-11-28-vscode-for-writers/vscode-for-writers/kyTwnMm4Pc-3776.avif 3776w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-11-28-vscode-for-writers/vscode-for-writers/kyTwnMm4Pc-3776.webp 3776w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-11-28-vscode-for-writers/vscode-for-writers/kyTwnMm4Pc-3776.png&quot; alt=&quot;VSCode showing project stats&quot; width=&quot;3776&quot; height=&quot;2322&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sounds-great-how-do-i-get-started&quot;&gt;Sounds great, how do I get started?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have some experience with software development tools, you&#39;ll have no trouble getting VSCode setup for creative writing. If not, it may take a little effort to learn a few new things along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you value a powerful tool that can be configured to support your way of working, then I think it&#39;s worth the effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Download &lt;a href=&quot;https://visualstudio.microsoft.com/#vscode-section&quot;&gt;Visual Studio Code&lt;/a&gt;, and give it a try!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know how you get on!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;❤️&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>We Need More Optimistic Science Fiction</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/blog/2024-10-24-optimistic-sci-fi/" />
    <updated>2024-10-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/blog/2024-10-24-optimistic-sci-fi/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As a genre, science fiction has a proud heritage of shaping the future. We find it entertaining to imagine what the world &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be like. Science fiction enables us to explore possible futures, and through exploring them, decide for ourselves what future we want to create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, the space-race of the 1950&#39;s and 60&#39;s, was driven by a spirit of optimism and excitement for humanity breaking free of the Earth to explore the solar system and beyond. While the influence of the Cold War cannot be understated, it was science fiction that inspired us. Through science fiction we imagined a future where space travel was possible, and this drove us to make it a reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We imagined a better future. We wanted it, and we created it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel we have lost this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science fiction has become dominated by dystopian and apocalyptic visions of the future, which for a time was entertaining. For a time, it &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; fun to imagine climate catastrophes, pandemics, authoritarian governments, economic collapse...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think you can see where I&#39;m going with this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reality is catching up with fiction. Cautionary tales have become our lived experiences. These worlds, into which we escaped for entertainment, now feel too close to our everyday lives. Consequently, we are less excited by our future, and expect less from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a new thought. Other people, much smarter than I &lt;a href=&quot;https://ariaste.tumblr.com/post/163500138919/ariaste-the-opposite-of-grimdark-is-hopepunk&quot;&gt;have made this observation before&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://festive.ninja/one-atom-of-justice-one-molecule-of-mercy-and-the-empire-of-unsheathed-knives-alexandra-rowland/&quot;&gt;and made it better&lt;/a&gt;. So I won&#39;t labour the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to focus on what we can do next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are losing our optimism for the future, and I think that science fiction has a responsibility to help bring it back. We do not need to be trapped in feelings of hopelessness. Through science fiction we can escape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;escaping-together&quot;&gt;Escaping Together&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fantasy is escapist, and that is its glory. If a soldier is imprisoned by the enemy, don&#39;t we consider it his duty to escape?. . .If we value the freedom of mind and soul, if we&#39;re partisans of liberty, then it&#39;s our plain duty to escape, and to take as many people with us as we can!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;― J.R.R. Tolkien&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science fiction and fantasy provide escapism, they allow us visit other worlds, different from our own. Ordinarily escapism is fleeting, a temporary respite from our ordinary lives into an exceptional fantasy. But Tolkien understood escapism to be more than this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He believed that escapism was a duty, a moral obligation to escape from the tyranny of the mundane. To free our minds from the constraints of our lived experiences to imagine a different and better world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that science fiction has a duty to help us to escape from a perceived future of hopelessness. To break out of a pessimistic view of our world, and to show us paths to making life better for all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is wrong to believe that science fiction is just a playground for unrealistic fantasies. Science fiction is a tool for exploring the possible, for imagining the future. It can change the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has done this before, it will do this again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we broaden our imaginations, explore the possibilities together then fantasy can become reality. Impossible can become inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-impossible-to-inevitable&quot;&gt;From Impossible to Inevitable&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only a crisis - actual or perceived - produces real change. When that crisis occurs, the actions that are taken depend on the ideas that are laying around. That, I believe, is our basic function: to develop alternatives to existing policies, to keep them alive and available until the politically impossible becomes the politically inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;― Milton Friedman&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friedman was an economist, political philosopher and Nobel laureate. He was a key figure in the development of the Chicago School of Economics, who&#39;s ideas became very influential in the 1970&#39;s and 80&#39;s, particularly with the Regan and Thatcher governments in the USA and UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not a fan of Milton Friedman, his politics and mine have little in common. But he did understand that for new ideas to be realised, they must become established long before they are needed. If we wait for crises to occur before we start thinking about solutions, we are already too late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that a lack of alternatives to our current political and economic ideas is a problem for the world right now. The crises in our current political and economic systems are obvious, we feel them every day. But our leaders (of all political colours) are stuck in the same old ideologies, repeating the same mistakes - we need new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there are new ideas out there, sometimes even good ideas, these are not yet well established enough to be seen as politically viable. In Friedman&#39;s terms, there are no &lt;em&gt;politically inevitable alternatives laying around&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your politics is your own, and I&#39;m not advocating any one idea over another here. What I am encouraging is a shift away from doom and gloom, towards optimism for our future. To get back the hope we once felt and a culture of ambition for a better world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science fiction can help by suggesting, exploring, promoting and establishing new ideas. By &lt;a href=&quot;https://festive.ninja/2019/04/26/the-uses-of-optimism-utopias/&quot;&gt;showing us visions of a brighter future&lt;/a&gt;, we will become excited by the possibilities of what we can achieve together, and be motivated to realise it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re trapped in the dream of the Other, you&#39;re fucked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;― Gilles Deleuze&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, science fiction has inspired us to &lt;em&gt;literally&lt;/em&gt; fly to the moon. I believe that science fiction has a moral obligation to inspire us once again, to help imagine a future that is better than our present, to make us hope for it, fall in love with it and want to make it reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feeling hopeless about our world, may be justified, but is not inevitable. I encourage you to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/culture/article/20220113-the-sci-fi-genre-offering-radical-hope-for-living-better&quot;&gt;seek out hope and optimism&lt;/a&gt; and, most importantly, to share it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine the world you want. Write it with passion, and share it with love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;❤️&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Near-Future World Building</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/blog/2024-10-22-near-future-worldbuilding/" />
    <updated>2024-10-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/blog/2024-10-22-near-future-worldbuilding/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;World building is, for me, one of the most enjoyable parts of writing fiction. Creating a world inside my head and exploring it through my characters is a lot of fun!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a fictional world is set in the near future, I may want it to feel familiar and yet otherworldly. To do this, I begin by thinking about the world as it exists today, and imagining what our future might look like as a springboard into creating a fictional world. But I don&#39;t need to rely on my imagination alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many forecasts available to learn what the world might be like in the future. If you&#39;re looking to bake some plausibility into your world-building (and it&#39;s fine if you&#39;re not!) then you may find these resources useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve focussed on global-scale data for population, age demographics, economy, and climate change, but many of the linked resources also provide data for regions and countries. In my commentary I&#39;ve highlighted some interesting points made in these forecasts, but I&#39;d encourage you to explore further to get a sense of what is expected in different parts of world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;world-population&quot;&gt;World Population&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the world&#39;s population continues to rise, population growth is slowing. The UN forecasts that global population will peak at 10.4 billion in 2086 and begin to fall before the end of the century. This growth will not be evenly distributed, with most population increase expected in Asia and Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 2100 it is expected that almost all people (85% globally) will live in urban areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In West Africa, a region of 9 cities including Abidjan and Lagos, is set to become the most densely populated region on the planet and could be home to 500 million people by 2100. The current largest urban area is the Greater Bay Area in China, home to 70 million people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may sound startling, but it could mean that in the future more people enjoy a higher quality of life than today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many examples — across broad areas of development — that suggest that, on average, living standards are higher in urban populations than in rural ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-10-22-near-future-worldbuilding/575aea6fDI-13083.avif 13083w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-10-22-near-future-worldbuilding/575aea6fDI-13083.webp 13083w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-10-22-near-future-worldbuilding/575aea6fDI-13083.png&quot; alt=&quot;World population growth, 1700-2100&quot; width=&quot;13083&quot; height=&quot;9584&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-10-22-near-future-worldbuilding/iWekXYzlvH-3400.avif 3400w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-10-22-near-future-worldbuilding/iWekXYzlvH-3400.webp 3400w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-10-22-near-future-worldbuilding/iWekXYzlvH-3400.png&quot; alt=&quot;Population by world region, 1800-2100&quot; width=&quot;3400&quot; height=&quot;2706&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/population-regions-with-projections&quot;&gt;Our World In Data: Population by Region Chart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/world-population-growth-past-future&quot;&gt;Two centuries of rapid global population growth will come to an end&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://es.weforum.org/videos/we-are-entering-the-era-of-the-megalopolis-supercities-connected-by-urban-sprawl/&quot;&gt;We are Entering the Era of the Megalopolis, Supercities Connected by Urban Sprawl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/urbanization&quot;&gt;Our World in Data: Urbanisation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;age-demographics&quot;&gt;Age Demographics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through the rest of the century life expectancy will continue to rise. Most people can expect to live longer, but this does not mean that the population as a whole will be older.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now there are relatively few people of working age compared to those who are not (the so-called &amp;quot;ageing population&amp;quot; crisis). But due to shifts in the demographic make-up, the working age share of the population is expected to begin rising by 2040, and continue to rise through the end of the century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-10-22-near-future-worldbuilding/KP8Ww6WxiO-3000.avif 3000w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-10-22-near-future-worldbuilding/KP8Ww6WxiO-3000.webp 3000w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-10-22-near-future-worldbuilding/KP8Ww6WxiO-3000.png&quot; alt=&quot;Population pyramid, 1950-2100&quot; width=&quot;3000&quot; height=&quot;2082&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-10-22-near-future-worldbuilding/RQGtJ7ILqm-3400.avif 3400w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-10-22-near-future-worldbuilding/RQGtJ7ILqm-3400.webp 3400w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-10-22-near-future-worldbuilding/RQGtJ7ILqm-3400.png&quot; alt=&quot;Age dependency ration 1950-2100&quot; width=&quot;3400&quot; height=&quot;2400&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/age-structure&quot;&gt;Our World in Data: Age Structure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;global-economy&quot;&gt;Global Economy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The growth of population in Asia and Africa will drive economic growth in these regions. By the end of the century, most of the world&#39;s economy will be focussed in these areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big gainer will be Africa, whose share in GWP will rise from 5% in 2020 to 39% in 2100. Within Africa, the growth in the global share will be slowest in Northern and Southern Africa, with their combined regional share falling from 49% in 2020 to 14% in 2100. The fastest growth will be in Eastern Africa, whose regional share will rise from 17% in 2020 to 35% in 2100.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relatedly, the share of people living in extreme poverty worldwide is expected fall below 2% in 2050, down from 8% in 2023. The World Bank defines extreme poverty as living on less than $2.15 a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-10-22-near-future-worldbuilding/coHeJf5Uv_-1076.avif 1076w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-10-22-near-future-worldbuilding/coHeJf5Uv_-1076.webp 1076w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-10-22-near-future-worldbuilding/coHeJf5Uv_-1076.png&quot; alt=&quot;GDP of world regions 2020-2100&quot; width=&quot;1076&quot; height=&quot;788&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ubss.edu.au/articles/2022/july/what-will-the-world-economy-look-like-in-2100/&quot;&gt;What will the world economy look like in 2100?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2023/04/extreme-poverty-eradicated-growth-think-tank/&quot;&gt;Eradicating extreme poverty by 2050?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;climate-change&quot;&gt;Climate Change&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s not possible to forecast the near-future, without considering the effects of climate change. Forecast scenarios vary, and are heavily dependent on action taken today, but it is clear that the world will be warmer, and sea levels will be higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tools like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sealevel.nasa.gov/ipcc-ar6-sea-level-projection-tool&quot;&gt;NASA Sea Level Projection Tool&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.floodmap.net&quot;&gt;World Flood Map&lt;/a&gt; can be used to visualise the effects of climate change on sea levels and coastal communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-10-22-near-future-worldbuilding/qKpJOYvX8r-1348.avif 1348w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-10-22-near-future-worldbuilding/qKpJOYvX8r-1348.webp 1348w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://example.com/blog/2024-10-22-near-future-worldbuilding/qKpJOYvX8r-1348.png&quot; alt=&quot;Global surface temperature and September Arctic sea ice, 1950-2100&quot; width=&quot;1348&quot; height=&quot;1400&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar6/wg1/downloads/report/IPCC_AR6_WGI_SPM.pdf&quot;&gt;IPCC Summary for Policy Makers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar6/syr/&quot;&gt;IPCC CLIMATE CHANGE 2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sealevel.nasa.gov/ipcc-ar6-sea-level-projection-tool&quot;&gt;NASA Sea Level Projection Tool&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.floodmap.net&quot;&gt;World Flood Map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-bright-future&quot;&gt;A Bright Future?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above are just a handful of resources showing what the world might look like in the near-future. While the population will be larger, more people will live longer and experience a higher quality of life than today - especially in Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that you find these resources useful in your world-building, but also I hope that you find them interesting in their own right. It is easy for us to feel despondent about the world, but there are many reasons to feel good about our future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re interested in this topic, I&#39;d recommend the excellent book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gapminder.org/factfulness-book/&quot;&gt;Factfulness by the late Hans Rosling&lt;/a&gt; which makes a strong case for optimism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take care and happy writing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;❤️&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why I Started Writing Late in My Life</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/blog/2024-10-18-late-life-writing/" />
    <updated>2024-10-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/blog/2024-10-18-late-life-writing/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I came to writing late in life. It had to wait until I was happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a common archetype of the tortured artist, the writer who writes driven by daemons and trauma. I am not that writer, as least not directly. I could not write while I was unhappy. While I was unhappy I struggled to create anything at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My childhood was a happy one. I was blessed with a loving home, full of fun and creativity. My imagination found outlets in painting, drawing, arts and craft - all encouraged by my parents. But as I grew older, I lost this. I no longer found joy in creating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was gone. I did not know why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back then people didn&#39;t really talk about mental health, especially not men. Depression was just &amp;quot;feeling sad&amp;quot;, and anxiety &amp;quot;being afraid&amp;quot;. These were not illnesses to be treated, they were just feelings to be dealt with. Keep calm and carry on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&#39;t know I was sad. I didn&#39;t know I was depressed. It was just the way I was. Every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my mid-thirties, something in my mind began to change. Perhaps it was parenthood, perhaps not, but I began to recognise that I was not happy. So I made some changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a very short space of time my life changed a lot. By my late-thirties, I was in a new relationship, a new home, I was working for myself. I&#39;d had counselling, which was transformative. My life before... that was someone else&#39;s. I felt very good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then at some point, I&#39;m not exactly sure when, my imagination came back to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inexplicably creativity flowed, unstoppable and relentless. Sculpture, painting, music, craft, all came back to me in an insatiable torrent. Having spent most of my adult life trying to wring out ideas from my mind, I was now struggling to keep up with the flood. I could not produce work fast enough to satisfy the pressure in my mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I began writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&#39;t plan on starting to write, I just somehow did. I had a story and it demanded words. I can&#39;t explain it any other way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This surprised me. I&#39;ve never been a writer. Though I&#39;ve always read a lot, I had never considered writing for myself. But then I did, and I found something new, something good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As much as I enjoyed my other creative outlets, writing gave me something else. It is so immediate. Straight from my brain into words. No waiting for the paint to dry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mind can breathe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now, I suppose, I am a writer. This blog is for me to write. If you read my words, I do hope you enjoy them, but if you don&#39;t, that&#39;s ok too. I am writing for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;❤️&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>